[Music]
hello Andrew how are you doing very good
strangely enough the fact you just said
strange to enough reveals that we're
right in the middle of the coronavirus
crisis exactly in this was a national
edition of Sweeney vs bird where we're
going to talk about that on different
levels so this is March 19 2020
so that you know if anybody looks at
this afterwards which obviously oh well
then you know that there was a specific
date in time and conditions for specific
at that date this is actually a former
philosophy of practicing right now
called EV ontology mmm-hmm ecology is
like what Heidegger and and and I'm
Badou and many other four losses dealt
with a lot of course if you're a process
philosopher if you do philosophy on time
and process and Relations like y'all so
dickfist and I do and he believed that
this is the fundamental aspect the
reality then certainly events is the
name the philosophical name for specific
things that happen throughout history
that changed everything forever once
they happen right and it could very well
be that the corona virus pandemic is
going to be one of those events yes
certainly stuff breaking into our
reality all aspects of our lives and our
reality yeah so if you talk say to a
really good epidemiologist they will
probably say this is not the big one you
know the big pandemics and history kill
children
they killed just about everybody they
kill usually 1/2 or 1/3 of population
that's not going to happen this time
around but it's looking very bad so this
is not Marx on TV it's looking very bad
in southern Europe at the moment where
you see the worse than it ever was in
China and and of course we're
sympathetic now with Italians and the
Spanish and increasingly the French who
are now suffering from yeah maybe maybe
we could talk about that I'm living in
in Paris and on full full on isolation I
can't go out in the street without a
piece of paper yeah saying that I'm
going for a walk for exercise or I have
to go to this pharmacy or go shopping
yeah I haven't
you know in a week pretty much getting
all the groceries delivered so
Scandinavia where I live we have a lot
of cases the very few deaths so far this
is March 19 it could of course get a lot
worse it could get like France or even
like Italy we know that but here in
Scandinavia we are more of a sort of an
improvised seam isolation so people take
responsibility for themselves you know
they they buy groceries for the
neighbors if the neighbors are elderly
or sick or anything and but we still go
to the shops
I would even out to a restaurant last
night to support the local you know
small business around here but we sat
very separately from other guests and we
minimize the risk here but it's far less
hysterical I would say than in France
but also we're either after the curve or
way more lucky when it comes to
Scandinavia so that's the situation here
on March 19 mm-hmm and and of course I'm
concerned in my 86 year old mother she
got out of surgery a couple of weeks ago
she's the feast just most wonderful
woman in the world but she lives in her
own house in the countryside and I have
a brother and sister look after her when
needed but we try to minimize her
contacts with the outside world
turns out it's heard about my neighbor
who had just had a stroke so and I'm not
supposed to go in contact her and yeah
normally we talk a lot and so it's a
very awkward situation you know it is it
is awkward
certainly awkward if your urban if you
live in a you know in a big city right
now but we know from Italy for a fact
already that the average age of the
people who die from this disease is 79
and a half no it is older elderly people
who are most at risk and people who have
certain previous dispositions and health
problems I've got to ask for my sauce
I'm actually listed on that list so I
should be careful I guess you know your
things go hmm we'll know more in three
months time obviously this is a
commentary you are making today where
the philosophy certainly will be
timeless but the news feed is specific
for March 19 it's there right so um so
we I was thinking like we could talk
about you know we as we're doing right
now what's happening now and and maybe
you could sort of predict what you think
is going to happen what the
ramifications
of this will be on all levels of society
and and also maybe since you know a lot
about history you could talk about what
usually happens and what are the
possibilities what what what are like
what are the dangers like let's say a
totalitarian dangerous of this kind of
thing and what are the possibilities of
reconstructing how we live okay so
epidemics and pandemics is like that's
part of philosophy every philosopher
you know writes about it's as soon as
the philosopher i'ts about the social
sphere you write by human beings you
have to you have to approach pandemics
and epidemics because they have there
are certain events or even trauma so I
would say the traumas in human history
so for example we have the two biggest
ones we suffered in the in the West at
least was was the big plague of the 6th
century they changed history forever you
know we talked a lot about of the
Persian Empire went down and the major
cause for the person in power went
darling
then in the next 100 years after that
plague was because the plague had killed
almost half the population on the person
and it was devastating
it didn't kill as many Arabs and as many
Europeans and that's exactly what Arabs
so the Europeans came to dominate the
Middle East in Europe after that they've
done so ever since but the Persians got
out of the way and and it sort of became
the Iranians we know today which is some
more of an isolated nation between East
and West but the golden era of the
Persian Empire was over by the by the
7th century and this was because of a
plague in the 6th century and of course
we have another plague that the
Europeans and Americans are familiar
wind that's the one for the 14th century
that was a massive plague that killed
about third of the population of Europe
he ironically also opened up for the
Renaissance afterwards the once things
get around but it takes a long time
we're gonna suffer from a major economic
recession follow this there's no doubt
about that we're gonna mass unemployment
I think it's a double tragedy for Italy
because Italy economy was already you
know totally in havoc before this
happened it's not gonna get any better
because of it so we don't know the
ramifications in that sense but and this
is not the big one even if it hurts to
say that considering your thousands of
people are dying in Europe at the moment
and possibly also soon in North America
but
the fact is that the big ones hit the
population a much wider scale hmm it's
up to a third or even half of the
population to die eventually for the big
plagues and this is not a plague in that
sense this is a virus and this is way
more serious than a regular infants saw
because a new virus as well it could be
have a mortality rate that could be up
to 10 or 50 times higher than normal flu
we don't know that yet so oh you're
going to do you have ways to deal with
this sort of thing that we didn't let's
say in the Middle Ages right so so so
maybe it would be much more lethal in
another context what so far it sounds
horrible but since it kills old people
already sick it doesn't kill the young
people of the future because if it kills
young people our future the damage their
overall damaged on society will last way
way longer much worse you could even see
a whole civilization go down because of
that that's not gonna happen in this
case obviously but but it is a danger
when the elders of the society die I
mean that yeah that's or something right
that's the yeah astray of the Society of
the leaders that oh you could ask gay
people for example they suffer from
their own pandemic called HIV in the
1980s and the 1990s before we got
medication that put a break to that but
most of the gay people I talked to and
I'm bisexual myself some part of the
LGBT movement them and most of the gay
guys today my generation of 59 they feel
that the generation older than me and
this generation that I belong to were
the ones who died right so you know the
shiniest brightest guys died obviously
slept around the most and they were in
most gorgeous so what was left was kind
of a pale coffee about the game um it
had been before that and then of course
they've done great work fighting for the
rights and you know fighting for not
being ostracized because of the deceased
they had and that work has been going on
since the early 1990s and it's now on a
global scale I mean you still have to
fight for a fundamental gay rights in
places like Africa Russia today in other
parts of the world gays have become
accepted by society they can even marry
and have children these days but if you
look at if you look at the overall
effects over the last 30 years
I think the gay guys would agree with me
that the whole culture as a whole is
suffered and that means all of culture
stuff you know what I always talk about
androgynous people should consider
themselves to be an important part of
the overall Society
yeah we always talk about the Georgia
State we should not never get out
separated from rest society they should
live in between men and women in the
middle of society in between what we
call the outer and the inner circles and
you can just look at like theater
theater has become very nostalgic you go
to Broadway they play the same old place
all over and over again and if they're
not old place is usually just a distant
movie turning into a musical right so
the lack of imagination the lack of
innovation in that area is enormous when
you can consider the fact the peanuts
are results you think of the people who
should have been in the original
playwrights today there are a few out
there like Bret Easton Ellis's guy and
he's fantastic but if you think if the
world should have had 40 or 50 Bret
Easton Ellis's rather than just one
uh-huh that's that's what we should have
had if eighths hadn't happened so the
damage done when the younger part of the
population get affected by disease it's
a cultural one also it's not just the
number of corpses of the number of
people who suffer or get sick and the
family tragedy is the go with that but
he's also a younger people died in in in
in the pandemic you get a massive
cultural effect as well come on society
as a whole that takes hundreds of years
sometimes to compensate for this is more
likely to be a decade or so but I don't
want to speculate too much on the rest
I mean I'm following the news every day
and I work with epidemiologist um I'm an
economic geographer by training as a
philosopher I do complexity theory this
is this is at the core of complexity
theory that a society is in itself
complexity theory and practice so it's
very very difficult to make the right
decisions at the right time you need a
deep understanding on history psychology
sociology social psychology political
science all these things and also one
country is different from the next you
can't just have the same model for
everywhere in some country cities it is
epidemiologist of the ultimate power and
other countries is the politicians of
the ultimate power and that makes these
that makes a major difference when you
make decisions and policies apply
policies and how you're gonna solve the
problem like this and of course also
some countries have invested in their
healthcare and some haven't and some
countries have universal health care in
some countries unfortunately health care
for the rich and few so we we have yet
to see what's gonna happen in in what we
used to call the third world in
countries like Pakistan Egypt and Brazil
where probably the virus is gonna strike
next and I don't even want to think
about how bad that can be if we're lucky
warm weather it could could be part of
the solution but we don't know that yet
right yeah as of March 19 we have no
idea you know it's a whole new viruses
so speculating on how it's going to
operate
judging from previous virus pandemics is
very hard mmm but back to philosophy
this is called event ology so what do we
mean by Evan Tala gee it's okay there
two ways of looking at the world you and
I explored this in the past in our the
web costume one of them is no madala G
and the other one is of ontology and no
modalities the fundamental story of the
human tribe on the move yeah sorry about
the the two patriarchs the priest the
chief Cain and the monarch who they're
responsible to and the movement of this
triad over time we see the pattern
returning in all the major religions so
we know for a fact that no modality is
something we can study today as the
narrative of the so siient
the original nomadic tribe and this
whole new science of sociology is
exploring how human beings developed
over a period of sixty to seventy
thousand years were not much changed and
precisely because not much changed the
world view essentially this one it was
that every new year usually the spring
you would celebrate the new year and
history would just repeat itself it
would just be a new here it literally a
new world would appear to you hmm
and and that year would close the next
spring when a new year would come yeah
so following every year because years
all busy circular you would have an idea
of time as being circular so everything
we just come back to the same point all
over again now what happens with
permanent settlements
years ago and that's also when things
like pandemics and epidemics become
problematic because we settled down and
eventually instead of just going to war
with our neighbors all the time we have
to make peace with them and we start to
trade with them now that's beautiful
because trade creates an abundance that
human beings have never seen before so
humanity explodes we go from at most 3
million people as a whole on the planet
during pure numerology we call it
interstate we mix we start a mixed norma
dalla ji no knowledge is still the
dominant mode in Chinese in Indian
culture Hinduism is an omen illogical
religion but we add to numerology
starting in Persia three thousand seven
I know we add the idea that we can have
an event ology is like a second religion
this is basically religion to begin with
for the military and religion for the
priesthood themselves eventually becomes
the more masculine aspect of religion
and and so Astron ISM is the first and
original ontology this white cells
associated with more efficient all the
more efficient might can you like just
flesh they're a little bit like what we
mean by M ontology religion linear time
it's linear time so it means that no
life does not repeat itself every year
it means that no the new year we're
celebrating this spring doesn't mean
that the world has just died of the
world has woken up again and be reborn
for another year when it's a story it's
a story of a forward progression of some
kind
yeah well development of it's a
developmental story basically yeah so
for example you take free day freeze
Nietzsche's philosophy it's centrally
understand he doesn't use these terms
the terms arrive later we deal Delors in
the 20th century when he reads nietzsche
and doesn't brilliantly if you want to
start a nietzsche you start by reading
to Mercer's book on each it's a great
great start then you can read Nietzsche
for himself after that but nature deals
with the fact that I with every return
of the same you know the term the term
returns
mmm-hmm but it's ancient
it's what circular time and circular
religion is all about Buddhism and
Hinduism and these religions are based
on it so the Nomad illogical return
return of the same Eastern there's
something is added to that in
essentially biological
it starts in the salsa it starts with
the nomads all in itself before we even
settled and he's a difference between
the relation between the son of the
father and the daughter and the mother
because in the relation with the
daughter of the mother in the world of
psychoanalysis the daughter just mimics
the mother mm-hmm that's all she needs
to do and she then gives birth to
children and these children are
different from the child she was when
she was a child but that's the only
difference you see within the matriarchy
and the father rebelled against the I
mean the son rebelled against the father
no not rebels he doesn't have to
necessarily but he's different he's
slightly different and this little
little difference he said the philosophy
is just like physics the small small
differences make a hell of a difference
at the end of the day always remember
that the small differences at this
specific point in time make a hell of a
difference later that somebody coughed
in Wuhan China probably in October in
2019 has turned the world upside down
on 19 March 2020 mm-hmm okay so small
things in biology and physics and
philosophy can make a hell of a
difference later on so the small
difference in the relation between son
and father in this also in the original
tribe means that the son is slightly
different from the father and this
difference of course we'll where we have
an identity did this is where I'm not my
dad
I'm not his jr. I am something different
from my dad is something that's
ingrained in the masculine identity
that's what we don't a matricide in
Sigmund Freud you don't kill the old
woman you just let her rule the tribe as
much as he wants to until she does you
don't question or authority dictatorship
is perfectly OK song it's on the female
side right but but on the male side you
separate the chief Cain and the priests
because you don't want the data ship
there because you're gonna lead you're
gonna follow you're gonna lead and then
follow into the future that's what
that's what the outer circle manhood is
all about and the fact that son is
slightly different from the father means
that with every loop of the eternal
return of the same the next loop is
slightly different hmm the new year this
year is not exactly the same as last
year
mm-hmm so this is a sounds like the
invention of time no linear time linear
time yes linear time what do they call
that in Greece
they differentiate between Kairos and
Chronos and in Greece they actually
difference between how we perceive time
and how it actually operates okay so so
no not even the Greeks the Greeks are
still within circular time I would say
most of the time they rarely leave that
concept is certainly predominant in
Plato and interact lives before him I
wouldn't say that the Greeks do not
really deal with linear time linear time
definitely comes to Europe through the
Hebrews it comes through religion so
biblical religion yes so linear time was
founded by so rostered that was his
biggest innovation more important than
monotheism and that later becomes
Judaism and we know that Soros Jones and
Jews
I've had a long love affair with each
other for thousands of years and it
starts when the Persians conquer Babylon
and they found a strange Egyptian sect
called the Hebrews in Babylon and they
set them free because the religion of
the Hebrews already are practicing with
a separate Yavin L or L in other night
they have two different aspects of the
divinity of God this exact like older
mosques are separating so after religion
they obviously felt they were a kid like
they get it and what reduced and God
from the person's was the idea of linear
time mm-hmm
so they started to write down their
Bible with the Genesis and with the
Exodus and everything and they rewrote
of course which was the founding
mythology of the Hebrew religion was of
course the exodus out of Egypt mm-hm and
this is where it gets interesting with
both Sigmund Freud and now we are
working in the same area with a new book
on Soderquist and I were following up on
Freud's Moses monotheism is that linear
time also hits the Egyptians in a big
way through it not on 1300 before Christ
right that's about 400 years after after
the linear time revolution is happening
Persia
the Persians not to separate the
chieftain in the priests but the
Egyptians try to unify them but that's
what dictatorship and tyranny starts in
Egypt 1300 before Christ was still in
the Bronze Age long before the
exhalation this is what the really
interesting things happen in human
history during the Bronze Age and the
deep chest and formulate through it not
on the idea of the chief Cain and and
and the priest must be the same person
mmm-hmm is monotheism in a dualistic
world so the duality moves from
chieftain and priest into you it's
internalized are you separate body and
soul okay the beginning of a sort of
schizophrenic dualism yeah that that
idea right existed because they already
build pyramids so doing I suppose
already rampant in Egypt and that I
think is why it was Egyptians who
invented that monic cult the Monica the
call to the one so this is this is like
the cult of the unified priests and
priests and chief came into one person
and then of course acknowledgeable there
was pure terror he died he's Sun
Tutankhamun's later murdered by the
priests were in speculating you and
either this could possibly be the origin
of Judaism and that's as Christianity
some of the mimicking Judas and we're
putting Christ on the cross thirteen
hundred years later but we all know that
the Jews rewrote the exodus out of Egypt
instead of just Moses leading the people
out of Egypt having one leader which
would it be more Egyptian they started
mimicking the Persian pattern the norm
at a logical pattern which was that the
chief to the priests must be separate
and that we got a match are pushing us
all forward and these are the three holy
siblings in Judaism that's why in the
Jewish returning of the Exodus are a Jew
is fundamental that there's Moses
there's Aaron and there's Miriam huh
Aaron is a chieftain Moses is the priest
and Miriam as the network okay that's
another kind of Trinity here Trinity's
again
Trinity is all over the place triads as
we call trails they're stable over time
because detroit's it is a mathematical
construction even the American
Constitution that would save America
today no matter what happens with the
coronavirus even the American
Constitution is built on the same kind
of tribe obviously Aaron is the
precedent Moses is to Congress and
Miriam is the Supreme Court same pattern
so a mythology that explodes because
nearly restore Astron ism any of Judaism
and in the Persian Empire as Thomas is
practiced as the overall religion for
the entire empire and they completely
tolerate accept even endorse the Jewish
religion as a separate religion within
so a stern ISM why do they do that
they do precise because the rest ISM is
a universal religion where do doesn't
what is practiced is the origin of
nationalism alienation say Israel nation
and ok again a nation state that we in
Europe of course started shaping up in
the nineteenth century after the big
European empires fell apart
so Empire as a concept is older the
nation way old the nation we both
empires as soon as we got out of our own
permanent settlement started coming
towards others but nationality we speak
the same language we write the same text
we recite from the same text so we can
practice the same religious rituals
starts with Judaism and what we then
inherit in Europe is this shared Persian
Jewish ancestry and that's when we talk
about European history we talk about
Athens and Jerusalem mm-hmm and we today
we discuss it like there's a history
philosophy and there's a history
religion mister philosophy starts with
the Greeks we call it Athens because the
religion starts with Jerusalem and
starts with the Hebrews
but actually that's dead wrong to begin
with only European culture separates
philosophy and religion to begin with
everything is religion everywhere else
in the world
philosophy is only the theory of
religion its theology essentially and
I'm adamant about that that's what we
should look at it so there really isn't
a home on philosophy or a home religion
here it's religion if laws are one of
the same thing and it's just that we
have linear time arriving from the
Persian Jewish ancestry meaning of
ontology in European culture has a
person Jewish origin mm-hmm and Noah
made ology is what we practice as the
Greeks of the rumors mm-hmm and it comes
out of Greek and Roman polytheism and
out of Greek and Roman philosophy and
literature mm-hmm okay that that is a
better way of looking at European and
American history today is it's a look at
the origin here it's a shared one where
no morality and haven't told you better
words than philosophy religion so it's
the way we perceive history and time and
what gives us meaning throughout time
because if it's everything a circle and
returns to the same you might as well
throw away as many things you possibly
can as you go along because history is
going to start
fresh from zero yeah with every new loop
but with EV ontology what's weird is
that suddenly it started write down all
of history you started right on who was
the son of whom who was the son of who
was the son of omoro son of a and you
get obsessed with the origin of the
tribe where do you where does your
family come from where does your tribe
come from what was the father you know
500 generations ago just seems to be
just you start to record human history
right yes that's what you're saying
yeah cuz you can write because you can
write because you have you cannot have
linear time without writing and I
haven't seen anybody make this
connection before but I think it's the
deeper connection is that we know we
settled permanently some eight to ten
thousand years ago starting in
contemporary Kurdistan and along the
river valleys this this way of living
spread and because it was highly
successful when it came to feeding
people the populations grow immensely
suddenly half the population of the
world lived in Mesopotamia and then
India and China and in Egypt became
populated and of course it's became a
waning model because you could create
large armies out of farmers coming out
of river routes right so that conquered
the world that model but it was also
tied to the idea you could write down
and you did write down you wrote down
everything that had to do with farming
you wrote down how many cattle you had
when you were started raising cattle we
also wrote down a new narrative and the
new narrative had to be one that wasn't
just made up by shame and now about
tomorrow in the trial I kind of want her
to be it out to be it had to be year
after year after year after year after
year and this new obsession with linear
time this event ology they became the
religions of the Middle East in Europe
okay so I kind of want to come back to
the present now because I was thinking
that yes we have we've had this recorded
history of this event ology is this kind
of religion and now we have the Internet
where everything is being kind of
recorded so so I wonder if you could
talk about yeah I mean what's going on
right now and if we could we could bring
that back to the the whole issue of
pandemics and and oh yeah yeah yeah
absolutely I mean
the benefit of writing down history is
that you do write down myths but they
represent reality I mean if you write a
myth if you go to mythos instead of
logos right know goes for example in
science logos is fact is mathematics
it's it's it's it's zeros and ones and
obviously you can only solve the
pandemic by going to logos mmm that's a
medical science that has to solve this
problem but mythos is sometimes the
better way of telling a story to teach
people how to live their lives properly
so say no one in the arc for example
obvious in this right so but the myths
are there in religion like Jordan
Peterson stresses all the time they're
incredibly important to understand to
understand why they're there and what
they teach us and obviously when you
look at the myths one of the things they
taught us early on when we started
writing them down was that the
conditions have changed and we become
permanent - settled now you have very
different problems in a permanent -
subtle society then you would have in a
nomadic society yeah right for example
you live it on the river flooding oops
okay how do you make young men dream
about irrigation so we can separate the
water distribute it over a larger piece
of land without getting flooding so I
like you created Delft on which you can
farm yeah well there have been flooding
all the time but it took thousands of
years for people to try to figure out
how to avoid flooding in some place of
the world they still have it and
flooding causes enormous havoc and kills
loads of people so if you know you've
got flooding already it's obviously
going to happen then obviously also
along the river while you're trading or
between the river systems while you're
trading which is the trade routes for
example the Silk Route is north between
is built between the major river valleys
of the middle eastern Asia and it's it
is the beginning and the end of all
civilization to be honest about the
city's amazing but obviously if you did
trade for you know a couple hundred
years every now and then along the trade
route also an innovation of an angry
little mob of nomads would happen like
the Mongols or a pandemic would spread
mm-hmm so all of history is full of
these pandemics yeah so all of us
there's foot of the floods it's full of
the pandemics and epidemics and these
things happen
now obviously they happen even more
today more than ever at a more frequent
level because we travel more and more
interconnected than ever before yeah but
for good or bad we also have cameras
everywhere and we have microphones
everywhere and we memorize absolutely
everything through our machines and
because we do this today we both can
spread the warning about a new disease
like we did out of one China that was
like five months ago from today harsh
lightning and all of the world knew
about it within weeks it's possible the
Chinese hit it longer than they should
have and that's also possible the
reasons why it's become so lethal and so
problematic but at least after a while
when that epidemic started spreading
into Han China and the major city was
sort of struck by the pandemic it became
known as the rest of world and the the
idea that this could spread far outside
of China and cost even more havoc
elsewhere suddenly took root and this
happened very very quickly so also know
we got tons of parallel studies around
the world to try to see if this is there
any medication that it sort of can put a
brake on this can help us out that's
also happening and there parallel
studies being done around the world they
put their studies online from day one so
they don't work and say Washington state
in America and Australia in China and in
Holland in so isn't this the first time
there's been a pandemic where where the
whole world has to react sort of so no
no that was ours
there was service which is closely
related to this and SARS was stopped
yeah SARS was even worse so let's let me
say the first pain ran slower yeah it's
a first and emic that's gone out of
control that we need to every but like
during SARS I didn't have to isolate
myself you didn't either I mean it's
everybod the Chinese thing effect yeah
that everybody in the world is being yes
yes so so yes that's correct
it's not I think better example is the
Spanish flu that happened at the end of
the first world war starting in 1918 and
that was trying to get killed almost as
many people as the war had and it killed
young people more than older people was
actually the opposite effect really died
and old people survived so the structure
of that flu virus is different from this
one
so the problem of this one is that it is
causing a lot of havoc and Italy in Iran
especially our two tragedies already
we'll see what happens next but and it
looks bad it looks really bad to be
honest about it but SARS was more lethal
then the copied 90 what the the name of
the virus is actually SARS - more or
less but it's copy 19 what we call the
infection and copy 19 though it spreads
easier and probably it's even so bad is
March 19 again that it looks the last
week it looks like it's symptomatic
spread of the virus actually it's
causing most of the problems that's what
happened initially in the office worried
what does that mean a systemic spread a
symptomatic means that unless you start
coughing and showing clear signs of
having the infection you're not
spreading it to anybody else
automatic means that you don't have
symptoms but you're still spread it and
that's the worse because you don't even
know you're six you're probably gonna go
on with your life the way you do so we
don't know the country towards mass
self-isolation in France in Italy and
Spain is based on the idea that the
problem in asymptomatic spread of the
pandemic is so serious that we have to
take it into the calculation otherwise
you would have healthy people are self
isolated yeah so we don't know yet this
is again March 19 but we can learn from
history from previous epidemics and
pandemics and certainly philosophy has a
lot to say about this especially when it
comes to event ology because once you
understand how important the authorities
become to us after written language
arrived and after he's settled
permanently and after look at all of
history all the way back back to the Big
Bang with the big Big Bounce it's
probably called now these 13.8 billion
years of history it would be impossible
for us as human beings to think of
history that way and that way far back
if we haven't invented the event
illogical religions without Zoroaster
Ness of Judaism Christianity and Islam
we wouldn't think of history that way
yeah we don't think of learn your
history at all but we do now and we do
both we both have a conception of
history like circular certainly for
ourselves of human beings because we
live and we die and hopefully we die
somebody inherits us and take over
everything and we can then transcend by
dying
letting somebody else take over and run
the world until their children then do
the same thing that is a very circular
concept of reality and that is
fundamental to human life we can call
that even the vertical know modality
rather than horizontal horizontal
modalities for the entire society moves
from the past into the future the
vertical no modalities your own life we
move from child to grown-up
- to parent or or elderly and and then
hopefully if you die one day you've
lived a full life you'll be respected by
the community and the honor you by
giving you a special place in their
history so that is all part of them will
become cold and vertical Norman ology
but the of ontology of history itself as
a series of events is different and this
is why things like choice you can I stop
you first like the event ology the
vertical of ontology is circular because
no no no event ologist does not have
anything secular about it at all but
it's an eternal return no no turn return
of the same is no mythology ok event
ology is just a flat time axis there's a
definite before and after you can never
go back when each reincarnation is
definitely tied to numerology in the
circular time it's impossible to think
an idea like we encourage it otherwise
it actually makes sense
it's a reincarnation well if you if you
your soul doesn't have a memory or so
might as well be reused for the next
life that's being born
it's the problem reincarnation is rather
problem if you memorize everything had
your life that you born old well you're
not supposed to about then it's all
reincarnation and this says that you are
incarnated rather it's life itself
that's being reincarnated human love is
being reincarnated a new generation is
born an old generation dies now that
makes sense and that's no matter logical
and it's circular yeah so the way you
did the way you deal with the no
mythology is pure no mythology like a
Buddhist of like at least Buddha did was
that you have to get out of this
circularity
there's no other way of solving the
problem and the only way to get out of
circularity is going to moksha and
Nirvana basically
disappear from the whole circularity and
Providence East exists once a row so so
you go towards ceasing to sister these
ceasing your desires ceasing to exist
that is that it makes perfect sense if
you are an omen ologist and nothing else
but if you're an event ologist and you
think that the world is literally
changing with every new generation we
human beings might look alike you might
think like in a brain capacity might be
similar from one generation to the next
but the life around us are involved as
it's called in German it's changing all
the time now I believe that be both
right we have versus yeah we have both
stories they're parallel then like we do
logo Smith or some pathos two different
ways of telling narrative in the first
place then what are the major narratives
what are the grand narratives you know
cynically start working on this grand
narrative trilogy and fundamentally
we're gonna divide into third books
divide the Normandy ology of ontology
they haven't all of these time just
standing out for a linear time became to
us ten thousand years ago because we
have to go beyond the seasons you cannot
just invest for this season they're not
for the next season yeah okay what am I
going to save in terms of seeds for the
next season well then the next ace is
not identical to this one I might have
more or less seats next season than I
did this London okay then one year is
different from the last year okay then
the years follow one after the other
okay then you get a time axis that is
not circular longer it's linear it can
you can go all the way back to the Big
Bang with the Big Bounce or even before
that and it can go as far as you like
into the future now
once you've accepted of ontology you
also accept that at certain dates
certain important things happen that's
why you and I are using EV ontology now
we're saying March 19
2020 no because our obviously our
discussion today here is so time
specific that's unavoidable concerning
the circumstances if I could just say
one thing you mentioned I think in our
last talk about was it Lacan and and the
imposition of the real right when the
real comes on yes and that that seems to
be
what I feel like I'm experiencing if I
can be personal very clever yes snobbish
chic is written about this if you look
at an event for society as a whole then
obviously September 11 comes to mind
yeah and if you and I would have sat
here on September 12 and had this
discussion he would have been avoidable
not to talk about it
mm-hmm and speculate about it because we
couldn't know that much on September 12
we can only speculate so we're in a bit
of the same position all right in the
middle of the corona pandemic hitting
Europe in a bad way were you and I live
it's March 19 so it's the same thing
we're in the middle of the event itself
it's impossible not to think about it
and that's when the real hits you and
and the way Lacan describes is that you
have two ways of you two kinds of
fantasies your imaginary fantasy and you
have your symbolic fantasy your
imaginary fantasies what you fantasize
about vague your abstract way and your
your more concrete fantasies the
symbolic one because it's tied to
language itself mm-hmm
okay so you live in these two fantasy
worlds you live in a fantasy world the
language in a fantasy world of pure
imagination and suddenly the real
breakthrough
you know talked about it when discussing
Joan of Arc in the past in our critique
of him that he doesn't really understand
where religion comes from religion is
how we deal with real yeah really didn't
always start with a thunderbolt in the
head and one of the guys in the tribe
know any dice whoa whoa no that that
about just killed my brother what the
fuck's going on right so pandemics
masters fit into this it's something
that you can't understand or digest it's
too much for you personally to deal with
on some level it breaks your fantasy to
begin with he just your fantasies like
what the fuck did I believe I'm living
in a fantasy this business reality and
suddenly what strikes you this is why
it's so divine what strikes you is
Rudolph Altos written extensively
Mountain is a mercy Elliot - but you
know the great I'm sure all of these 20
said you've written a lot about this but
religion starts with the fact that oh
something interrupts breaks into your
fantasy and you perceive it as reality
itself September 11 was clearly that the
current corona pandemic is clear that
because it's like we suddenly
know that nobody's in charge of society
yeah it also when it's no father here
there's no mother nobody's taking care
of us we will be rising about we've been
theorizing about a breakdown of some
kind yeah for a long time yeah actually
happening is very different than all
this this theorizing yes yeah and still
it is a breakdown and still it could be
the worse it's like the worst thing to
comprehend right ah that's why I say
Auschwitz and the Second World War is
still a trauma with us it is definitely
a major event or at Rome I feel like
it's sort of a negative impact event
it's what we call the trauma right so
major social trauma is of course the
concentration camps and the Second World
War in general Hitler and Stalin one
hundred million people dead in Europe
right we're still we think we thought
about it
ignore it after 1945 I'll deal with it
but but you know we opened the
concentration camp doors at about the
same time that we exploded the first
atomic bomb over Hiroshima yeah how
could he possibly say history hasn't
changed since then mm-hmm that is
ridiculous and that is why I'm adamant
that EV ontology today is even more
important than nomad ology to understand
the times we live in of course for a
Christian there's a before and an after
Christ of the cross mm-hmm now produce
in his arrest ins they disregard that
completely and and juices Erastus agree
probably just a mad Gnostic who Caiaphas
for all the right reasons executed so we
got rid of him because otherwise things
will be work much worse off the Dusen's
are asked and thought how Jesus in very
high regard at all but of course the
question is do because him dying on the
cross this that is the before and the
after event is the major exactly this
and it's possible that the killing of
Tutankhamun was the major event the
kick-started Judaism it's very possible
that's what happened this is so for when
you approach event illogical religious
they're very different from Buddhism
Taoism and Hinduism the mythological
legends or asterism and ayah hammock
religions are different in this as a for
them the events are key to understanding
the human condition
this seems to be uniquely Western isn't
it event no it's Middle East Middle
Eastern Middle Eastern East and it's not
Western I don't want to miss a Western
yeah because what had you Manik but it
seems to be oh no no West Western was
the Greeks and the Romans and the pagans
and they were all circular they were all
like the Hindus are today they were the
one circle immense it's the revolution
starts with a reformer all Iranian
religion which who was harassed her
three thousand seven years ago with the
publication of the gothis this could
really be the event among texts
published more so than the Bible because
it added of ontology to the human
understanding of the world and so roster
is adamant that he's aware of this the
entire text of the gothis is about the
difference between annulments they're on
the move and the people who decided the
permanent to settle and he knew the
people who permit the subtle would then
have history they would have a Year Zero
this is where we settled before that
history only repeated itself there is no
counting of time there's no there's no
calendar
there's no calendar there's no calendar
before you settle permanently there's no
there's no need for account that starts
with a year zero and then as a year one
and a year or two and a year three and
year four hmm right and then you have
eventually when new events happen that
you claim are more important than the
original event then you get Christian
existed well Christ on Christ was born
so because he was born that's more
important than the birth of the first
text so we're gonna make this year zero
and then we have before years hero
before Christian error and after okay
and the must substitute the same thing
later they don't even have child month
and their calendar is very confusing but
you know if you're gonna be totally
honest about it
year series should be the publication of
the gothis which is about three thousand
seven hundred seventy-five years ago
because that date to your history that's
the first event the first event
according to event ology according to
linear time first like okay I see it's
within like the story of humanity begins
at this point yeah linear time it only
existed temporarily within circular time
before that it exists in men existing
the outer circuit because
their time is the beginning of logos
well okay but what about like in a Haida
Indian group they have their stories
about the origin of their their clan and
and and how it came to be and yeah but
it's different they'll be what is the
difference yeah the difference is that
they will then celebrate that every year
No
so if you may see early odd goes through
these stories anthropology is that so if
there's a birth of the world at a
certain point in time then every year at
that time the world is being reborn
mm-hmm therefore there is no specific
date for the birth of the world itself
mmm okay
it's the same time every year so say you
celebrate midsummer which old pagans do
it was still doing in in you know post
Christian Scandinavia a midsummer is
like the the longest day of the year the
shortest night which is end of June and
you celebrate that because it's the peak
obviously the calendar and it's the same
eight every year that's eternal return
because they're exactly
erna lee whereas an event like
coronavirus or yeah Jesus or whatever is
it changes history yes yes so yeah you
could say even that the corona virus
pandemic is currently structured is an
event the influenza virus the returns
every winter is it typically
neurological mm-hmm phenomena so we
don't use the word event for that try to
use the word event only for of ontology
is where it's specific in timing unique
that's the way Heidegger and and and and
by do you use it before me and said it
is so so event all it is about that
rather in the Norma dalla ji it's a
ritual so I've never ever here in
Scandinavia heard a Scandinavian talk
about the first midsummer yeah it
wouldn't know it's incomprehensible it's
just no midsummer celebrating at the
midsummer and Midsummer's have existed
forever yeah got it
so that is no nology yeah that's
Neurology and you will discover that
what's interesting is that women
actually take more to Norma knowledge
and mate it men take more terminology
hmm in general population there's a lot
of women are brought into dermatology
and there's a lot of men who are very
good know-it-all
but overall in terms of populations
again we see these patterns of a large
populations that when you come to the
outer circuit and hunting and warfare
activities that dominate that circle men
arm usually located young voice is fired
to be heroes when they grow up to be
part of the outer circle and doing the
other men and going through a rite of
passage all those activities that take
place that are much more geared towards
of ontology so I've been told the
existed whether the tribe that he sort
of broke down all this more masculine
because men want to construct the future
right yes and when they're a good at
remembering birthdays and women are
gonna want to remember birthdays and
also take care of the community and it's
a great split it's not a problem it's a
great asset that's a different for one
tonight even though we take care of the
pandemic we'll discover that certain
female traits are very useful women are
very very very good at carrying the beat
the shit oh man here men are usually
better at saved overall planning we were
gonna go we go to put the resources not
not there's a lot of women who good at
that job the men in general more
specialized at that also the irony here
is that so far also the virus has hit
more men than women and one man that we
know it has I didn't know that there's
no women the female body has an
advantage apparently when it comes to
how it reacts to the virus and that's
also very common it you know it's men
often die younger and under more violent
circumstances the women do mm-hmm right
and that is because of the structure of
the body they're more vulnerable
physiologically more vulnerable mmm
interesting yeah the opposite right you
would think that stronger more
physically stronger but that's probably
prize than pay for being physically
stronger interesting but you also you
mentioned something we started playing
around with a new word who were working
with now and you're we all know that
said acknowledge each other exit all you
so Ditka past neither I love this word I
love this I love this word because it's
something it's like this is what has to
be done exid ology yeah in a way like
think of all the institutional
difficulties of dealing with the corona
virus and i'm thinking about what needs
to be done as a teacher i'm thinking
about schooling and education and that
kind of thing
and that is it need what needs to be
done is to move from the old dead
structures into the new whatever that
yes yeah so what happens now is that the
exid ology of our time is obviously the
move from physical into digital so that
was ironic to accelerate because of this
this is smart seems to be already March
19 we're in the middle of a huge
financial crisis across the Western
world is still Amazon announced
yesterday they're about to employ a
hundred thousand more people in North
America so all this year
II tried is taking off in a massive way
at the moment ecommerce around
restaurants and hair salons and all the
small bases I think the large companies
would be saved but but the small
companies are gonna have a hell of a
time over the next few months to survive
right so that's the real economic
tragedy is going on at the moment and
that's also why the isolation probably
has to be broken sooner or later also
for economic reasons otherwise although
society falls apart but when this is
happening would you talk about it's an
EXO dolla jia plied in our times makes a
Dalek is going on our time is what's
Atticus I've written in all our books
this is the paradigm shift from an urban
physical society / - a virtual digital
society yeah
- moving online and we're doing in a
rapid pace because obviously you and I
can have this conversation and we
concern you not Trevor I know it's
totally weird I teach 25 hours of
classes a week and they're all online
now and all these lot of people who
couldn't do this kind of shit their way
in the old in the past or having to
learn all this these new structures and
communicate with each other in a totally
different way and yes and this is an
exodus it's too happy about that
because I could stay at home and work
you know and I don't have to go take the
train I'm sorry to be speak so
personally I know we're talking about
larger things than than just just me and
you but
ya know but this is happening overall I
mean there's no set backs to the digital
realm at the moment it's moving it
forward fast and quickly and taking over
the old structures and we've talked
about this for the last thirty years
obviously this is an exodus right a
paradigm shift for all of society and
all of the world is moving in that
direction so exid ology is the study of
exodus so which are the big Exodus is
all history and how do they operate some
of them are physical like exodus out of
Egypt exodus out of Babylon or say when
Europeans moved on masse from Europe to
North America in the 19th century there
was a huge Exodus oh so you have these
big movements throughout history and
people moved from place one to place to
look but it of course we moved all the
time we were nomads so no madala G would
would mean a kind of permanent exceed
ology so that would be a realm of
permanent Exodus today's global.nomads
to travel what they have travelled until
now they probably locked up somewhere
now a few months but usually the global
moment to travel all the time gonna fly
everywhere and who lived their lives in
airport hotels and things like that part
of that circuit myself they are
obviously nomads of today and no no
Matala G therefore returns in a big way
because understanding yourself as a
person who's on the move all the time
makes sense in every wood that's
beneficial so if you can be global
moment it turns out that's that's why
you have a career while you're
successful you you get the lifestyle you
desire then obviously Nomad ologies the
right word for that but the a clinic
serology that we work with here really
is also what's important here if you're
gonna unify numerology and have ontology
mm-hmm and try to tell a shared story
mm-hmm the shared story would have to be
called the accede ology mmm-hmm because
it is unifier I'm not yeah so how do you
describe a society today where both
history is so important and when we have
these events for example now the corona
pandemic and we have the event of 1982
which was the arrival of the Internet
you know we have the event of the World
Wide Web arrival in 1992 we have these
major technological and also epi
geological events that are happening
around political events are happening
September 11 was neither a Jew it was a
political military event even so all
these things that are happening around
these events that set the history of our
time we certainly think of those are
very important and are before us and
after to all of us that we share because
of them and then we have the nammed
ology which is like well everything
returns to the same we got to get used
to dying when we die we don't believe it
gonna live forever any longer maybe we
never did what does it mean to transcend
then what does it mean to have a
spiritual quality to your life what does
it mean to really go deep and try to
find the right paradise your life like
you know solving the meaning crisis we
would say Camilleri so I would say that
we need both no mythology and of
ontology and made my critique of Havarti
when I'm critiqued him for not having
found us in 30
it's that his world is two no matter
logical and not event illogical enough
the unsub sound between Buddha and Plato
and they're both no matter logical in
circular it doesn't deal with the fact
linear an event illogical still is
incredibly important to human beings
made is still the most important that
spectrum or human life and that's where
I returned to Zoroastrianism and I
returned to linear thinking and linear
timelines because we must have that kind
of history too otherwise you just repeat
the same mistakes and linearity we can
come back to your word take a coat on
I'm gonna take your coat o penis and for
example to take the proper response to
the environmental crisis okay if that
Christ is going to be solved you can't
just lock down the entire world and go
poor and then die and kill each other
because then we have billions of people
dead at the end right that's not a
viable alternative I'm afraid I'm not
saying great that makes that connection
I'm afraid of the connection between the
greater to embrace or environmentalist
fanatics and and concentration camps
eventually I think that's a scary
route that we won't avoid at all costs
so you have to have an immature logical
approach to that and they were too
logical approach that is that say that
if very mentalism is a norman ology or
how we deal with the climate crisis
then a koto pianist is an air ontology
of how you deal with the climate crisis
you build better technologies mm-hmm
you saw their problem or a new and
better technologies you build sensors
you put those sensors indices you put
them in the sky you you tax carbon
that's where environmentalists and Acuto
pians agree you tax carbon so you can
get you know fossil fuels out of the
system in your air cleaner air yeah that
would be the latest at the air if anyone
in the past week here that's only
temporary sorry about yeah I know the
oil prices also falls at $27 so you know
so you got probably gonna burn more or
the gas than ever was over
that's the try the other times you know
it's all a problem it's spring spring
flowers are exploding here and there's
clean air and that's temporary yeah
that's clean air at the tremendous cause
a tremendous cause and that's an
enormous cost if you don't understand
that you're nave environmentalist and
you can you you know I'm on a part of
the debate because the cost right now
for having that specific clean air it's
more like the cost of all people having
died yeah and all these pieces are
really stuck in their little apartments
it's terrible I know I what you're gonna
see is that people are gonna drive more
cars than ever a month from now rather
than riding a bus or the subway so we've
got a more pollution than ever so this
current state on March 19 it's not the
state we're gonna arrive at once the
pandemic is over it's gonna get worse in
many different aspects before this is
over that's guaranteed right now yeah
and and uh but I think it helps to look
at the world as an ontology in this
sense okay something major happened the
real broke into our collective imaginary
and symbolic fantasies yeah we have to
deal with the fact that the gods have
run amok and it causes havoc on us and
it's it's time to number one of course
not sit and make podcast like you and I
do to be honest about it take care of
your neighbors isolate your mom take
care of the people at risk find out
who's at risk learn every day the new
stuff that's coming on science is now
producing new truths every day learn
every one of them wake up our morning
during meditation then go straight into
the news feed
learn what's the latest news and then
don't find yourself on the map what can
you do the most tell yourself and those
you love and care for I think that's
that's the number one priority right now
mm-hmm
so then we can learn the lessons
afterwards it's way too early to draw
the conclusions but there is a long
history demyx and pandemics philosophers
complexity theorists obviously
epidemiologists and doctors and tons of
other people out there study these
things they're prepared for them
unfortunately politicians haven't been
as prepared the resources we need right
now in Europe are lacking that's going
to be a major problem unfortunately a
lot of people are gonna die because of
that
because we too cheap on having enough
medical equipment around that's another
lesson we need to learn and we need to
remember eyes that lesson and keep it
for generations because otherwise we
repeat our mistakes all over and over
again and this is the case for event
ology the case for mythology is if I
stay in a normal and logical circular
timeframe and I'll never live it I will
always repeat the same mistakes every
term a new pandemic comes along the only
way I can't repeat those mistakes or
improve on the situation compared to the
last time it's through an ontology so a
couple of things that this virus or
whatever is going to help us with I mean
we could say is it will increased
hygiene will well will shift to home
schooling will well they'll be
technological acceleration hopefully
right I don't know I mean there could be
a lot of very positive innovations as a
result you can't you can't you can't
tell yeah you say a lot of technology
innovations that cost money right now
we're in the middle of a huge economic
crisis you got a lot of coins though the
only might have invented you know you
can't say that you can't say that
there's hopeful and great stuff coming
out of this chance okay what's gonna
happen
prepare yourself for a big mess for the
next few years and a major massive
economic recession
mm-hm and that's not we innovates yeah
at the end of it there could be a period
of innovation coming out of it
to be honest about it there's a lot of
scientific products that would be folded
because of this crisis too because they
would like like Fundy mm-hmm and the
total focus on solving the virus problem
at the moment means that even if you're
running to traffic accident today on
your way into Paris yeah I'll be last in
line and you probably die at the
hospital because of the traffic accent
because yeah okay so no I'm not denying
all any of that I know III I don't want
to talk about the positive effects in
corona virus pandemic right in the
middle of it I think it's just it just
smacks of escapism to me now I think
it's much better to look at the ongoing
spiritual revolution that's happening
but right now it's not about sitting
there praying it's all about going out
knocking on your neighbors doors and ask
them if you can help them out with
something that's that's really how you
become a real Mensch right now in the
middle of the crisis and and then we
have to compare in Europe we compare the
different constant can we please avoid
the Italian disaster or now the Italian
Spanish disaster
can you avoid in the rest of Europe well
hopefully we can and hopefully Italy and
Spain can be better off three weeks from
now but it's gonna take weeks for this
to change maybe even months and we don't
know where the damage is going to end
right now we're March 19 and it's just
it's just I think it's a waste of time
to speculate when you can actually go
out and help your neighbors okay I agree
a hundred percent more spiritual
approach right now we have we just we've
just seen our fantasies about the world
crushed